Okay, so in this video
then we're going to be
talking about reaching
a consensus in Agile.
And this specifically refers to Agile,
to Agile teams, because remember in an
agile environment, the team members are
the ones that are determining the work
that needs to be done, how
long the work is going to take,
how big of an effort the
work is and so and so forth.
Remember in an Agile
world, project managers
are not delegating work
to two team members.
Okay.
Now, the other thing I want to point out,
just from an exam perspective,
is I really just as an exam tip.
All right, let me start again.
So the other thing I just want to point
out as an exam tip here is don't confuse
these terms with the agile prioritization
techniques that we've talked about in
another video and the
agile estimation techniques
that, again, we've talked
about in another video.
These terms can sound very similar, it can
be very confusing in an exam environment.
So you have the Agile Prioritization,
you have the Agile Estimation,
and then these terms that
we're going to talk about
in this video, the Agile
Consensus Techniques, right?
Make sure you don't get these terms
confused.
Now, there are four basic consensus,
four basic ways of coming to a consensus,
right, at least four basic ways that you
need to know for the PMP exam.
Now, first of all, though, before we start
talking about these four basic methods,
let's think about exactly what we're doing
here.
What does this actually refer to me and
what do we need by reaching a consensus?
Consensus for what?
Well, let's think about this.
We talk about Agile.
Agile teams are responsible for the work
that they're performing.
So the Agile team is responsible for
determining the priorities of user
stories, right, for each particular
sprint, they're responsible for
determining how long activities are going
to take, or rather the level of effort of
each activity, the level of effort of each
user story.
They do that during release planning,
during sprint planning.
So that's what this consensus refers to,
right?
You have a whole team that's coming up
with these estimating, right?
They're estimating the level of effort.
They're prioritizing for each particular
sprint, each particular iteration.
We all have to agree, right?
Team members have to agree.
They have to come to a consensus,
right?
Different team members are going to have
different ideas, different opinions on how
long an activity is going to take or the
level of effort of a user story.
They're going to have different opinions
on that, different ideas on that.
So we need to reach a consensus.
And that's really what these consensus
techniques refers to.
All right.
So the first one here mentioned, then,
is something called the fist of five.
The fist of five.
as the name suggests, right?
You could either have a fist or you could
have five fingers.
So reaching a consensus here.
Everybody agrees, right?
Who agrees, right?
So let's say we're looking at the size of
a user story.
Or at this user story is a medium size,
right?
Who agrees?
Everybody agrees, or rather you agree,
you raise five fingers, right?
Just like a wave.
You hold up five fingers.
If you disagree, completely disagree,
then it's a fist.
right, you hold up your fist, right?
We disagree.
And then there's levels of agreement and
disagreement, right?
So whether you hold up, you know,
one to four fingers, right?
So there's different degrees of,
you know, agreement or disagreement.
So basically, you agree or disagree with
reservation.
So you hold up five fingers, completely
agree.
You hold up four fingers or three fingers.
I agree, but with some reservation.
You hold up two fingers or one finger.
I disagree with some you know and we need
to discuss it further right whereas you
hold up no fingers you hold up your fist
that means you completely and utterly
disagree right and of course team members
then you know they'll discuss amongst one
another eventually to a consensus then you
have something called Roman voting right
and Roman voting is just a fancy name for
basically thumbs up thumbs down that's
literally all it is and it doesn't have to
just be used in agile it's used in in
many, many situations, but thumbs up,
you agree, you know, team members agree or
I agree, thumbs up, right, I disagree,
thumbs down.
Simple as that.
Then you have polling.
So you're polling now, your team members,
right?
So everybody shares their point of view,
And then if it's a unanimous, yes,
you move on.
If there's an objection, then we discuss
it.
So again, as a simple example, right,
we're looking at one particular user story.
Right.
So, we think this is a medium-sized user
story.
Who agrees?
Does everyone agree?
Everyone agrees.
Unanimous decision.
We move on to the next user story.
If one person disagrees, no, I don't think
this is a medium size.
I believe this is a large size user story.
Now we need to stop.
We need to discuss.
So team members then discuss, you know,
whoever decided or whoever is saying that,
you know, I think this
is a large user story
instead of a medium-sized
user story, right?
Then, you know, they have the opportunity
to discuss why, and, you know,
there's going to be discussion back and
forth until, you know, until we come to a
consensus, and then we can move on to the
next user story.
And then something called the dot voting,
right, which is similar to like the
100-point method that we talked about in a
different video, right, or monopoly money,
and basically you have these sticker dots,
team members have these sticker dots.
It's more, it's like a game storming type
of thing.
You have these sticker dots and then use
these sticker dots to prioritize different
items, prioritize different user stories
or activities.
And, you know, some of these maybe color
coded, like red, yellow, green or all
these different colors and different colors
refers to different levels of priority.
Or it could also be numbers, the number of
dots that you have, the more number of
dots the user story has, the higher the
priority, and so and so and so forth.
So there's another way of reaching a
consensus.
So these are the four
basic tools for reaching a
consensus that is often
asked about on the exam.
I mean, in reality,
there's many, many more,
but these are some of the
four more common ones.